<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Little Plastic Bags]]></title>
  <link href="http://littleplasticbags.github.io/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://littleplasticbags.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2014-06-04T22:17:20+05:30</updated>
  <id>http://littleplasticbags.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Rahul D'souza]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Guilty until reinterpretation]]></title>
    <link href="http://littleplasticbags.github.io/blog/guilty-until-reinterpretation/"/>
    <updated>2014-06-04T20:57:51+05:30</updated>
    <id>http://littleplasticbags.github.io/blog/guilty-until-reinterpretation</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The Maharashtra Police have <a href="http://timesofindia.indiatimes.com/india/maharashtra-police-to-crack-whip-on-those-who-like-offensive-facebook-posts/movie-review/35974198.cms">decided to book</a> those who like &ldquo;offensive&rdquo; posts on Facebook. The police are using the recent violent protests over post derogatory towards certain personalities and historical figures that were posted on the social network.</p>

<p>The problem begins with interpretation. What constitutes a derogatory or &ldquo;offensive&rdquo; post? Let us take a look at the law under which the police plan on prosecuting their new classification of internet &ldquo;criminals&rdquo;.</p>

<p>The law that the police wish to implement is the Information Technology Act, 2000 (Amended in 2008), whose <a href="http://deity.gov.in/sites/upload_files/dit/files/downloads/itact2000/it_amendment_act2008.pdf">Section 66A</a> states,</p>

<blockquote><p><strong>66A. Punishment for sending offensive messages through communication service, etc.</strong></p>

<p>Any person who sends, by means of a computer resource or a communication device,—</p>

<p>(a.) any information that is grossly offensive or has menacing character; or</p>

<p>(b.) any information which he knows to be false, but for the purpose of causing annoyance, inconvenience, danger, obstruction, insult, injury, criminal intimidation, enmity, hatred or ill will, persistently by making use of such computer resource or a communication device,</p>

<p>(c.) any electronic mail or electronic mail message for the purpose of causing annoyance or inconvenience or to deceive or to mislead the addressee or recipient about the origin of such messages,</p>

<p>shall be punishable with imprisonment for a term which may extend to three years and with fine.</p></blockquote>

<p>It is pretty clear that the wording of the law is ambiguous and open to interpretation, posing a real threat to free speech online. This particular section has not gone unnoticed, with the Supreme Court of India putting restrictions on how an individual may be arrested for infringing this law &mdash; basically stating that <a href="http://ibnlive.in.com/news/prior-approval-must-to-arrest-under-section-66a-supreme-court/392152-3.html">approval of an officer of a particular rank</a> must be sought before any arrest.</p>

<p>This restriction, however, does not do any damage to the bite of this law. Countless individuals have had charges leveled against them and subsequent arrests and court hearings have been reported in the media.</p>

<h4>Criminalising speech after the act</h4>

<p>It is obvious that because of the ambiguous wording of the law and the lack of any clear guidelines on what separates &ldquo;objectionable&rdquo;, &ldquo;derogatory&rdquo; or &ldquo;offensive&rdquo; posts from an individuals right to speech and most importantly to critique and express opinions on other individuals, puts everyone at risk of prosecution.</p>

<p>Furthermore, selective prosecution of offenders, based on violent protests as a defininng factor, means that society is further confused about what is and what isn&rsquo;t an offense.</p>

<p>The only conclusion that can be drawn from this is that any individual expressing an opinion, or, as is the current case, liking an opinion online, may be subject to criminal proceedings according to the whims and fancies of the police.</p>

<h4>Are we losing our right to equality before the law?</h4>

<p>It appears that the only instigation to use Section 66A of the Information Technology act is the act or perceived threat of violent agitation.</p>

<p>While certain levels of descretion must always be available to law enforcement, this is an unnatural situation. The message being sent out is that if you should fall foul of certain pressure groups in society, only then will you be prosecuted by an ambiguous law that places too much interpretative power in the hands of the police.</p>

<p>Thus, if you happen to be of a certain world view or a certain community, organisation or political leaning, you may find that you are suddenly unequal in front of the law as opposed to people that enforce their world view through force or the threat of force.</p>

<h4>In conclusion: The criminalisation of thought</h4>

<p>Being prosecuted for agreeing with something but not acting on that agreement are the hallmarks of an authoritarian state, one in which, at least on paper, we do not belong. Isn&rsquo;t the simple act of liking a post (even one that is already at a disadvantage of prosecution itself) the same as owning a book or listening to a speech, that suddenly gets deemed illegal? Aren&rsquo;t the police overstepping their mark and entering the private domain of an individual&rsquo;s or even a community&rsquo;s mind and criminalising mental consideration or even specifically agreement?</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A New Blog]]></title>
    <link href="http://littleplasticbags.github.io/blog/a-new-blog/"/>
    <updated>2014-05-27T00:00:00+05:30</updated>
    <id>http://littleplasticbags.github.io/blog/a-new-blog</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>When I set up this blog I decided to use an old name, associated with an old blog. The contents of the previous blog represented a way of thinking to which I subscribed but lacked finesse and care over language.</p>

<p>I decided to use Octopress on Github pages for a few reasons. First, Octopress is incredibly easy to set up &mdash; as far as standard static websites go. Second, static websites are incredibly fast. Third, I was fed up with the Wordpress workflow. Finally, I also found the experience equal parts frustrating and fun.</p>

<p>I hope that you like this blog and I hope that you are not annoyed by the lack of comments. I find that most commenting systems have lost out to avenues like Reddit, Twitter and Facebook. I do not like to regulate opinions but could be tempted to do so with any commenting system and thus prefer to leave it to the general debating corners of the internet, should anybody care about any of this at all.</p>

<h4>About</h4>

<p>My name is Rahul D&#8217;souza. I am a researcher of art history and culture, a freelance editor, and occassional writer.</p>

<p>I studied the history of art and archaeology at the School of Oriental and African Studies in London and worked in publishing at The Marg Foundation in Mumbai.</p>

<p>Besides art history, culture and archaeology, I also have interests in and occassionally write about music, philosophy, politics, geography, economics, technology and futurology.</p>

<p>Find me on Twitter: <a href="http://twitter.com/rahuldsouza">@rahuldsouza</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
